# Curriculum Vitae

## Sanjay Chopra

15 Lookout Rise South Morang VIC 3752 Phone: +61 3 94369346 Mobile +61 450 079 994

Email: chopra5@hotmail.com

## Summary

I am a Solution focused Business Manager offering over 35 years of experience and have demonstrated the leadership needed to effectively deliver results and encourage teams to focus on a common goal.

I am recognised as a strategist, forward thinker, overcoming challenges to ensure performance goals and objectives are met.

Currently running a successful retail business and pursuing a career in full-stack programming.

In my current and previous roles I have been involved in

- Strategic Planning
- P & L responsibility
- Team management
- Contracts Negotiations
- Tendering & Bidding
- Channel management
- Operations Management
- Product Management
- Full-stack programming (HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, Bootstrap, Bulma, Node.js, Express.js, SQL, NoSQL, Sequelize, React, MERN)
- Object-oriented programming (OOP)
- Model-view-controller (MVC) architecture

I am a passionate and committed Business Leader, with extensive experience in leading and motivating teams to meet team and organisation objectives.

I have a strong background in developing and commercialising new products technologies and markets in Australia, India and Middle East.

I have an extensive experience in sales of Water and Waste Water technologies, chemicals and services to Municipal, Mining, Oil & Gas and to a range of diverse industries ranging from manufacturing, automobile, power to Food & Beverage.

# Professional experience

# 2015 - Present: Director, Sai Samarth Investments PTY Ltd, Melbourne, Australia

- Successfully established and run a retail business since 2015
- Oversee all aspects of the business, including sales, marketing, operations, finance, and customer service.

- Manage a team of employees and ensure high levels of productivity and customer satisfaction.
- Implement strategic plans and initiatives to grow the business and improve profitability.

# 2023 (Expected) - Graduation: Full-Stack Programming Bootcamp, Monash University, Melbourne, Australia

- Currently enrolled in a full-stack programming bootcamp to pursue a career in software development.
- Learning various programming languages and frameworks, including HTML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, Bootstrap, Bulma, Node.js, Express.js, SQL, NoSQL, Sequelize, React, MERN, OOP, and MVC.

#### 2010-2014 Business Manger- Mining

#### **Orica Watercare**

- P & L Responsibility
- Sales and Marketing
- Team Management
- Strategic Planning
- Contracts Negotiation
- Introducing new products, services
- Identifying new markets and applications
- Product Management
- Customer Relationship Managemen

### Achievement

- Developed Strategic Direction and planning for the business.
- ◆ Cumulative Annual Revenue Growth of 30% achieved
- Cumulative Annual Profit contribution growth of 40% achieved
- Successfully introduced range of chemicals to grow it into a highly profitable multimillion dollar business
- ◆ Successfully established Operation & Maintenance business

# 2007-2010 National Sales Manager

#### Amiad Australia Pty Ltd.

- Sales and Marketing of water treatment systems and solutions
- Managing Sales team.
- Technical proposals and presentation
- Cost Estimation
- Coordinate project execution
- Coordinate after sales service

- Customer relationship management
- Member of the organization Management team.

#### **Achievement**

- Setting strategy direction for the projects business
- <u>◆</u> Instrumental in securing major contracts valuing \$1 M+ each
- Successfully launched standard treatment systems
- ◆ Successfully added service business

#### 2005-2007

#### **Technical Sales Manager**

### Osmoflo Pty Ltd.

- Sales and Marketing of Water treatment systems
- Managing team of Sales Specialist and Design Engineers.
- Investigating and designing optimum processes.
- ♦ Tender preparation
- Cost estimation
- Coordinate with project team during project execution
- Liaison with major suppliers
- ♦ Member of core Management team of Osmoflo

## 2004 to 2005

#### **General Manager (North Operations)**

## Ion Exchange India Ltd

- ♦ Sales & Marketing Management
- Team Management and development
- ♦ Strategy development and implementation
- Tender estimation and preparation
- Preparation of techno-commercial processes and bids
- Coordinate and manage Project execution
- ♦ Key Account Management and client relationship management
- Channel Management

## 1995 to 2005

#### Director

## Ion Exchange Services (North)

- ♦ P &L responsibility
- Strategic Direction
- Provide technical advice/consultative services to customers to optimize the water and waste water processes.
- ♦ Provide after sales and Operation & Maintenance services.

#### **Achievement**

- Instrumental in making and sustaining Northern Region no. 1 in terms of business volume and profitability.
- Services of Northern region rated best amongst all regional locations and rated best in the Industry by customers.

2000– 2003	Divisional Manager, Ion Exchange (India) Ltd.	
1997 – 2000	Sr. Regional Manager, Ion Exchange (India) Ltd.	
1995 – 1997	Regional Manager, Ion Exch	ange (India) Ltd.
1993 –1995 (India) Ltd.	Manager- Engineering,	lon Exchange
1991- 1993 Ltd.	Sr. Technical Executive,	Ion Exchange (India)
1989- 1991	Technical Executive, Ion Ex	change (India) Ltd.
1987- 1989 Ltd.	Technical officer/Trainee,	Ion Exchange (India)

## Education

**B.Tech (Chemical Engineering)** Indian Institute of Technology (IIT), Delhi 1987

Senior Management Program from IIM Ahemdabad 2004